<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A nicke for neuters. A most godly and fruitfull sermon, begun and preached at Paules Crosse, the 30. day of October last, and continued &amp; finished in Paules Church, on New-yeeres day at night. / By Thomas Burt, Preacher of the Word.</title>
            <author>Burt, Thomas, preacher of the word.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00991</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4132</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S126041</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">44920314</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 44920314</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173760</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00991)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173760)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2095:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A nicke for neuters. A most godly and fruitfull sermon, begun and preached at Paules Crosse, the 30. day of October last, and continued &amp; finished in Paules Church, on New-yeeres day at night. / By Thomas Burt, Preacher of the Word.</title>
                  <author>Burt, Thomas, preacher of the word.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[85] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Simon Stafford.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: [par.]⁸, A-D⁸, E³.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation III, 14-17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173760:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173760:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Nicke for Neuters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A moſt godly and fruitfull</hi> Sermon, begun and preached at Paules <hi>Croſſe, the</hi> 30. <hi>day of October laſt,</hi> and continued &amp; finiſhed in Paules <hi>Church, on New-yeeres day</hi> at night.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Burt,</hi> Preacher of the Word.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>How long halt ye betweene two opinions? if the Lord bee God, follow him; but if Baal bee God, then follow after him,</hi> 
               <bibl>1. Kings 18.21.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Seene and allowed.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by Simon Stafford. 1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:173760:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173760:2"/>
            <head>To the right Worſhipfull Sir Iohn <hi>Grange, Knight, one of his Maieſties</hi> Iuſtices of the Peace and Quorum, in <hi>the County of Middleſex: and to that</hi> right vertuous, the Lady Katherine his wife, all earthly and heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true happineſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this dangerous time of Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, raging in this our Mother City, and places adiacent, it might be ſayd, as ſometimes it was of Rome, <hi>Paucorum vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus cuncta Romae patrauit.</hi> Your Worſhip, right worthy Knight, being one of this paucity, incumbe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t on your office in theſe places, euen alone <hi>Moſes</hi>-like, from the Morning to the Euening, bearing the burthen of the people, in hearing, deciding, ending their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies, mayntayning the vertuous, &amp; puniſhing the malefactors; and like a broad Fig tree, ſuſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the weake and little ſhrubs, making ſhaddow to the weary, giuing fruite to the hungry, and bearing your ſelfe ſtrongly againſt all peruerſe &amp; importune winds of contradictions and diſcouragements, yea, ſowing vertue, and reaping fame; with griefe haue ſeene, and well doe know, that it might be ſayd yet agayne (notwithſtanding Gods reuealed wrath and ſharpe puniſhments) as ſometimes it was of Rome:
<pb facs="tcp:173760:3"/>
               <hi>Moribus antiquis res ſtat Romana viriſque.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſoſtome.</hi> fayeth, If thou ſeeſt a tree doeth beare no fruit, the cauſe is in the root. The cauſe of the barren leaues of the peoples trees, and their vayne words, and abominable workes, I take it to be want of Religion, and Neutrality in Religion: I haue therefore made choyce of this text.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I entitle this booke, <hi>A Nicke for Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> becauſe this our age hath brought forth many a prodigious <hi>Polypus,</hi> and vayne ayre-full Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions. The diuine Angels of our Churches haue bene vilipended, God hath bene offended, and our City grieuouſly puniſhed.</p>
            <p>God auert his future further plagues, &amp; turne his Iuſtice into mercy, and giue vs grace by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to meet with his iudgements. The Lord ſtirre vp the heart, and bleſſe with all wiſdome, our pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſucceeding <hi>Salomon:</hi> inſpire with his ſpirit, and giue fit ability &amp; cunning to <hi>Bezaleel,</hi> &amp; <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holiab,</hi> to promote the worke of the Tabernacle. God rayſe vp (eſpecially now) truſty <hi>Chuſa,</hi> prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and iuſt <hi>Samuel,</hi> bold <hi>Elias,</hi> playne <hi>Iohn the Baptiſt,</hi> inſtant <hi>Paul,</hi> and feeding <hi>Peter:</hi> and extirpate and explode wicked <hi>Achitophel,</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous <hi>Iudas,</hi> blind <hi>Elymas,</hi> and paltry <hi>Magus,</hi> and graunt, that the Fig leaues of authority, paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, ſelfe-loue, flattery, deſſembling, and fond fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, may be pulled off from Madam <hi>Pſacentia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:173760:3"/>the noble Lady <hi>Verona</hi> may ſhew her liniaments, in vninueſted &amp; vnobſcured nakednes: ſo that with circumciſed hearts and catechized ſoules, we may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one bring the Arke of God into our houſes, while we may; that our houſes may be bleſſed, as thoſe houſes were where the Arke was: and that this famous City with the Suburbs, and adioyning Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, now after their late ſorrowfull ſighing of that <hi>Hei mihi, quanta de ſpe decidi,</hi> may (as it was ſayd of Chriſt) <hi>guſtare poſt fella fauos,</hi> to the glory of God, the Church, Common wealth, and our priuate good, And as by good deſert induced, it is my bounden duty, I beſeech the moſt Higheſt, to ſtretch out his hand of protection, &amp; defend, receiue vnder the couerture of his wings, and preſerue your Worſhip, and your vertuous Lady, with thoſe toward Imps, your two gracious ſonnes, &amp; modeſt courteous daughters: and to ſend with this my New-yeeres gift (ſuch as I haue to giue) which I commend vnto you, many new yeeres, and continuall new and true ioyes, benedictions and graces temporall, corporall, ſpirituall, celeſtiall, and eternall, for his Chriſtes ſake, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips in the Lord,</hi> Thomas Burt,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:173760:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173760:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Reu. 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="14">14 And vnto the Angel of the Church of the Laodiceans, write, Theſe things ſayth Amen, the faithfull and true witneſſe, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the creatures of God.</p>
                  <p n="15">15 I know thy works, that thou art neyther cold nor hote: I would thou wereſt cold or hote.</p>
                  <p n="16">16 Therefore becauſe thou art luke-warme, and neither cold nor hote, it will come to paſse, that I ſhall ſpue thee out of my mouth:</p>
                  <p n="17">17 For thou ſayeſt, I am rich, and increaſed with goods, and haue neede of nothing, and knowest not, that thou art wretched, and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and poore, and blind, and naked.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O ſpeake briefly of ſome, and pretermit other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces: The Pen-man of this prophecy through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole booke of the Reuelation is <hi>Iohn,</hi> that diuine Eagle, Eagle of diuineneſſe, one of
<pb facs="tcp:173760:5"/>the Lambes twelue Apoſtles, The time when, on the Lords day, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.10. called the firſt day of the weeke. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2.</p>
            <p>The obſeruation of this ſeuenth day is of diuine inſtitution, &amp; ſo hath bin from the beginning. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7. It is naturall, morall and perpetuall. <hi>God bleſſed the ſeuenth day, and hallowed it.</hi> The place, in the Ile of Pathmos, lying in the Aegean ſea, whither <hi>Iohn</hi> was exiled by <hi>Domitian,</hi> the Romane Emperour, about the yere of our Lord 96. for the Words ſake, and for the teſtimony of Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.9. The Perſons to whom, are all the ſeruants of God, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.1. Although but ſeuen Churches are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, yet vnder them, all others are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned.</p>
            <p>The true end and vſe of this booke, is to publiſh to the world all things heerein co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained, as they muſt be orderly fulfilled, euen to the end of the world, <hi>Cap.</hi> 1.1.</p>
            <p>This Booke of the Reuelation may fitly be deuided into three viſions, as it were into three generall parts. The firſt viſion, contained in the three firſt Chapters. The
<pb facs="tcp:173760:5"/>ſecond, in the next eyght Chapters, from the fourth to the twelfth. And the laſt viſion, contayned in all the conſequent Chapters, from the twelfth, to the end.</p>
            <p>This Chapter then is part of the firſt viſion, &amp; containeth ſeuen Epiſtles written to the ſeuen Churches of Aſia, wherein the preſent eſtate of the Churches of Aſia, is moſt liuely deſcribed, and in them the eſtate of all the Churches then militant on the face of the earth.</p>
            <p>Foure things are contained in euery one of theſe Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>Firſt, an Exordium or entrance into the matter. Secondly, a generall propoſition. Thirdly, a narratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Fourthly, a concluſion.</p>
            <p>The Exordium contayneth two things in euery Epiſtle. Firſt, the perſon to whom. Secondly, the perſon from whom this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle is written.</p>
            <p>The propoſition and concluſion, is in euery Epiſtle one and the ſame.</p>
            <p>The narration put between them both, conſiſteth of praiſe and diſprayſe, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, reprehenſions, threates and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173760:6"/>
            <p> This text then conſiſteth of three parts of this Epiſtle, written to the Laodiceans, the laſt of the ſeuen Churches. Firſt, of Th'exordiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, noting vnto whom it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, in theſe words, <hi>And vnto the Angell of the Church of the Laodiceans write.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of the perſon from whom it is ſent, which is here deſcribed by three Maieſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call titles. Firſt, he is called <hi>Amen,</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in theſe words, <hi>Theſe things ſayth Amen.</hi> Secondly, <hi>The faithfull and true witneſſe.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>The beginning of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The propoſition is the ſame as in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Epiſtles, <hi>I know thy works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Narration contayneth, Firſt, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion for a crime, which is, <hi>to be ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cold, nor hote.</hi> Secondly, A demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the cauſe of the crime, which is, worldly riches, and ſpirituall pouerty, in theſe words, <hi>For thou ſayeſt, I am rich, &amp;c.</hi> Thirdly, The threatning, which is, of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, <hi>Therefore becauſe &amp;c. it will come to paſſe, that I ſhall ſpue thee out of my mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the generall propoſition, <hi>I know thy
<pb facs="tcp:173760:6"/>works:</hi> I haue lately,
<note place="margin">At Lam beth</note> before many right reuerend and learned, already intreated, as alſo of the firſt part of this Exordium, to whom this Epiſtle was written.</p>
            <p>Now reſteth (Right Honourable, right Reuerend, Worſhipfull, and beloued, that I ſpeake of the reſt of theſe parts, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the words in order as they lye. And firſt, of the Maieſticall titles here giuen to our Sauiour Chriſt: <hi>Thus ſayth Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Firſt, he is called <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis word <hi>Amen,</hi> is a ſtrange kind of ſpeach in the beginning: for we are wont to end with the ſame word that we now begin. So as it may ſeeme by this beginning, that we make an end, when we doe begin: and by this conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing, to begin agayne, when wee haue made an end; as though wee had neuer made an end, and neuer begun. Yet in this is no prepoſterous ſpeaking, if we marke a diuine beginning: for the order of this ſpeach declareth the efficacie of his name,
<pb facs="tcp:173760:7"/>and the effectualnes of the name, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty of the Sonne of God, whoſe Name it is. For as <hi>Amen</hi> is here in order firſt, and otherwhere laſt, it reſembleth his nature, as he is called, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.4. <hi>Primus &amp; nouiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus:</hi> The firſt and the laſt. And as <hi>Amen</hi> beginneth, and <hi>Amen</hi> endeth: ſo is hee aſwell called, <hi>Reu.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Alpha,</hi> the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; as <hi>Omega,</hi> the ending.</p>
               <p>And as <hi>Amen</hi> is one word in all langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: ſo is he one and the ſame in all his Saints.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amen,</hi> as <hi>Aretius</hi> noteth, is <hi>vox appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantis fore:</hi> a word, ratifying and willing a thing to be; ſo to ratify and ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to all, before any thing be done at all; and with whom all things are done, as ſoone as he ſayth <hi>Amen. Pſal.</hi> 33.9. <hi>He ſpake, and it was done; he commaunded, and it ſtood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as <hi>Amen</hi> is the end, finiſhing, and laſt addition to all ſayings: ſo is he ſayd to be the finiſher of our fayth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2.</p>
               <p>As the Hebrue word <hi>Amen,</hi> ſignifieth <hi>verò, certò proculdubio:</hi> ſo is he ſayd to bee <hi>Amen,</hi> two maner of wayes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:173760:7"/>
               <p> Firſt, in reſpect of Gods promiſe. For 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. <hi>All the promiſes of God, in him are Yea, and are in him Amen, vnto the glory of God, through vs:</hi> that is, are ſealed ſure and firme, confirmed in him, through Gods good will towards vs in Chriſt le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.17. <hi>This is my welbeloued Sonne, in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi> Witneſſing, that though God was diſpleaſed for our ſinnes ſake, yet he is well pleaſed, and his wrath appeaſed for his Sonnes ſake. For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, we cannot attayne to Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. Therefore is he called our peace, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.14. and our bond, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.36.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in reſpect of the trueth of his natures. For how could be performed the worke of the worlds expiation, vnleſſe he had bene both God and man? Man, to be borne vnder the Lawe: God, to fulfill the Lawe. Man, to ſuffer; and God, to ouercome.</p>
               <p>Loe then, how this word <hi>Amen</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his nature, whileſt it ſetteth him forth to be the ſtability of all his promiſes. <hi>Amen,</hi> that is to ſay, that God; that verity, that is
<pb facs="tcp:173760:8"/>eternity; that man, that is the ſeat of mercy; that nature, that is charity; that power, that is victory; that peace, that is vnity; that life, that is felicity; being eternall, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; euerlaſting, without ending; infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite in himſelfe; the firſt and the laſt; vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in his Saints, as a Bride in her orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; amiable in his Church, as a father in his charge; infallible in his word, as a prepotent performer; admirable in his works, as an Almighty Redeemer; imperial in the heauens, as a ſoueraign Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; ineſtimable in the world, as an inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſtible treaſure of all the gifts and graces of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The faithfull and true witneſſe.</head>
               <p>HEre the latter expoundeth the former. Chriſt the faithfull and true witneſſe of God, which declareth to vs faythfully the true will of God: for in Scripture God is ſet forth to be the inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehenſible mind, and the Sonne, his diuine and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly
<pb facs="tcp:173760:8"/>word: becauſe, as the inward mind is made knowne by the vocall word, ſo the will of God is reueyled by his Sonne, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.27. And in this ſence he is <hi>Amen,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of vs: in the other he is <hi>Amen,</hi> in reſpect of God; for that he performeth the word of God, and carrieth it as an Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to vs, as heere he commeth from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and witneſſeth to men their vnkindnes and cold affection to God: and therfore to furniſh himſelfe, aſſumeth theſe adiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of credit, wherwith men ought to be prepared, when by the ſway of an othe the truth in ballance ought to be poyſed. The firſt is faith. The ſecond, truth. The third, knowledge. Fayth, for integrity; truth, for equity; knowledge, for certainty: for that euery ſuch witneſſe muſt know the matter in queſtion, without doubting, ſpeake that he knoweth, without lying, and continue faythfull, without corrupting. <hi>Adhibenda eſt fides, ne teſtimonium violetur; veritas, ne mendacij arguitur; cognitio, ne ignorantia aberremus.</hi> Theſe 3. properties are deriued from the tongue, from the heart, and from
<pb facs="tcp:173760:9"/>the conſcience: he muſt ſpeake what he knoweth, know what he thinketh, thinke in heart what hee knoweth: by meanes whereof theſe three parts in man, giue due honor to God: The conſcience, by teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying; the heart, by ratifying; the tongue, by ſpecifying the truth, which is required of three perſons. Firſt, of God. Secondly, of the Iudge. Thirdly, of the innocent. For God looketh on the heart: the Iudge trieth by the tongue: and the innocent hangeth on the conſcience. So that heere we ſee three notable aſſiſtants to confirme credit. Firſt, an vpright conſcience. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, a faithfull heart. Thirdly, a true and ſincere tongue: By whoſe iuſt teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the truth, Gods honour is confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the Iudge is informed, and the wrong is reformed.</p>
               <p>But if faith, truth, and knowledge be ſo neceſſary in a witneſſe of credit; what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of perſons are they, that for fayth, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce falſhood; for truth, lyes; and auouch their owne knowledge, contrary to their owne conſcience: and ſo bring a guilty
<pb facs="tcp:173760:9"/>conſcience, a falſe heart, and periured tongue to the ſolemne Iudgement ſeate, where that high God doeth ſit as chiefe Preſident, and the Iudge, as his authorized Lieutenant, to heare and trye, &amp;c. 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 19.6.</p>
               <p>Whereby it followeth, that the falſe ſwearing wretch doth not onely lye to the Maieſty of God, but alſo in calling him to witneſſe, brings forth the euerliuing God, to maintayne that his lye is true: and ſo makes the God of trueth (as farre as in him is) to be his ſtale to betray the trueth, his aſcociate in the villany, his conſort in the iniury, the colour of his trechery, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of his periury.</p>
               <p>Wherfore, ſeeing they beguile men vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of God, and make the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God their curſed meanes to bring their wickedneſſe to end: as they in the higheſt degree abuſe the ſoueraigne good, and ſo commit, of all others, the moſt haynous crime: ſo doe they merit, of all others, the moſt grieuous payne.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:173760:10"/>
               <p> Lamentable examples whereof haue bene ſhewed to this wretched world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Melancton</hi> reporteth, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. of one <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho,</hi> Biſhop of Mogunce, that he was, for wilfull periury, firſt ſtrooken by thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynt from heauen, and afterwards carryed by Deuils viſibly to hell, who yelling out as they went, this audible cry, <hi>Sic luendo, lues, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ruendo, rues;</hi> gaue their warnings to ſuch miſerable miſcreants, to take heed of GODS all-ſeeing eye, and ſeuereſt Iudgement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> maketh mention, <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. of three falſe varlets, accuſing <hi>Narciſsus,</hi> Biſhop of Ieruſalem, by falſe othes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſeuerall imprecations againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to confirme their affirmation: the firſt, that hee mought bee burnt with fire; the ſecond, that hee mought be conſumed to death; the third, that hee mought not ſee the light (if their teſtimony were not true) that the firſt was conſumed with burning; the ſecond, waſted with py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; and the third made blinde with
<pb facs="tcp:173760:10"/>weeping.</p>
               <p>In howe deepe deteſtation (thinke you) doeth the LORD hate this crime, ſince hee himſelfe doeth in the Lawe, <hi>Numb.</hi> 5.11. ſet downe the puniſhment, by an Oracle from heauen, and inflict it with a miracle from earth, inſomuch that, in women, that forſware their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continency, thoſe parts that offended, with ſwelling and rottenneſſe periſhed?</p>
               <p>For ſeeing that by periury, GOD himſelfe is diſhonoured, trueth abiured, conſcience defiled, Iudgement deluded, Magiſtracie abuſed, the innocent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, the guilty abſolued, the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous wronged, and wrong-doers ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunced; what maruayle, if God bee thereby moſt highly offended, when the world thereby is in perill to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded?</p>
               <p>Falſe witneſſe and periury, is the ſpeare and ſhield of all iniury, the throne and Crowne of all villany, the ſtayne and ſhame of piety, the ſcumme and ſome
<pb facs="tcp:173760:11"/>of fallacie, the founder of iniquity, and confounder of integrity. In whome, amongſt all other ill practiſes, this is moſt deteſtable, they worke all their falſhood, vnder a colour of trueth, and compaſſe all their wrongs, vnder the maſke of doing right, and performe all maner of iniquity, vnder the veſture of Chriſtian duety.</p>
               <p>Is not an othe the ſtabliſher of all trueth, determiner of all ſtrife, the tryer of all right, the diſcouerer of all falſhood, the ground of all iudgement, the end of all controuerſie, the witneſſe of all righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe towards men, and of all feare and worſhip towards God? <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Thou ſhalt feare the Lord God &amp; ſerue him, and ſweare by his name, &amp;c. Deut.</hi> 19.15. <hi>One witneſſe ſhall not riſe againſt a man for any treſpaſſe, for any ſinne, or for any fault that hee offendeth in, but at the mouth of two or three witneſſes ſhall the matter be eſtabliſhed. Mat.</hi> 18.16. <hi>That by the mouth of two or three wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, euery word may be confirmed. Heb.</hi> 6.16.
<pb facs="tcp:173760:11"/>
                  <hi>An othe for confirmation, is amongſt them an end of all ſtrife. Ier.</hi> 4.2. <hi>And thou ſhalt ſweare, The Lord liueth, in truth, in iudgement, and in righteouſnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ſo; what tryall can bee of trueth, what inuention to find out fraud, what Sanctuary to ſuccour right, what refuge to reſcue wrong, what end of Lawe, what vſe of Iuſtice, what Iudgement ſeate, what Princes throne, what credit in men, what regard of God, if the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend and ſacred religion of an othe fall to ground?</p>
               <p>Aſſuredly, theſe falſe and forſworne Vipers doe more hurt by vayled villany, then doeth the enemy by armed hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; perſonated in <hi>Synon.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>—Capti dolis, periuri<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> arte Synonis,</l>
                  <l>Quos ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Tydides, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Lariſseus Achilles, &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Synons</hi> periured tongue wrought more woe, and ſhed more bloud, then <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles</hi> percing launce. The one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into the field, like a man; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the Court, with falſhood,
<pb facs="tcp:173760:12"/>like a Deuill: the one, with weapon in hand; the other, with poyſon in heart: this ſtriketh his priuate enemy with the ſword; that, the publike Magiſtrate with deceyt: this man impugneth his mortall foe; that beaſt repugneth the ſacred lawes and iudgement ſeat of God: he, to repell the conceyued iniury; this, to ouerthrow Iuſtice, trueth, and equity: ſo the one doth aſsault with valour and magnanimity; and the other deceiue by ſacriledge and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery.</p>
               <p>But what doe I compare them to men at Armes, with their villany who goe (if it were poſſible) beyond the deuil himſelfe in this wicked witchery?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Medea</hi> confeſſeth, that ſhe could by the helpe of <hi>Hecate, Ripis mirantibus, amnes in fontes redire ſuos facere,</hi> by her incantation, make Riuers runne backwards againe into their fountaines, turne ſtreames backward, and roots of trees vpwards: a thing very prodigious. But theſe, by their inchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting periury, can doe a great deale more
<pb facs="tcp:173760:12"/>then that: for whereas ſhee could onely inchaunt by her charmes, riuers, hilles, woods, herbes, ſtones and trees: theſe can bewitch equity, trueth, Iudgement, knowledge, and authority; and by their blacke arte turne them ſo contrary, that they can transforme good into ill, light into darkenes, truth into falſhood, equity into iniury, verity into vanity, authority into tyranny; make the defender the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer of the world, and tranſmute the comfort of men into confuſion.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, although they both ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe the Name of God; the one by ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, the other by periury: both defile Gods creatures; the one by coniuring, the other by abiuring: both worke won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the eye of the world; one vnder the viſor of piety, the other by open in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity: Yet in this, the Coniurer doeth inuocate the deuill, the Periurer, the Name of God; this infecteth the earth, that infeſteth the heauens; this worketh on corporall bodies, that on ſpirituall
<pb facs="tcp:173760:13"/>minds; this on trees &amp; herbs, that on ſtates and Cities: the one oppoſeth his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt the things of this world, the other his deuiliſhneſſe againſt the Throne of God.</p>
               <p>No doubt, the very damned Witches are ſo much the leſſe in their doings haynous, then the periured Swayne, as it is more impious to abuſe the inviolable Maieſty of GOD, then the ſubtill Deuill; and thoſe heauenly treaſures, then the earthly creatures: For when hee hath done all this miſchiefe, hee maketh the iuſt God his cloake, to couer all his abominations: So that he infecteth the very heauens with the breath of his mouth; the very ayre, with the venome of his tongue; and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth euen very hell, with the malice of his heart.</p>
               <p>O earth, earth, earth! corruption, for fouleneſſe; carrion, for vileneſſe; fleſh, for frayleneſſe, how dareſt thou ſay to Gods moſt ſacred Maieſty, Couer my periury: and to that inuiolable Verity, Be a ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow
<pb facs="tcp:173760:13"/>to my lye: and to the Iudge of all righteouſneſſe, Bee my copeſmate in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe?</p>
               <p>Was there euer ſinne of ſuch a ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe face, obſtinate heart, yron-ſinewed necke, and brazen brow, as to ſay to the Searcher of the heart, and Tryer of the reynes, Witneſſe my witneſſe to bee true, when he lyeth in his heart? O incredible impudency! ſurpaſſing <hi>Tytion</hi> in oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briouſnes; <hi>Gorgon,</hi> in prodigiouſnes; and <hi>Cyclops,</hi> in contemptuouſnes: yea, the Deuill himſelfe in wickedneſſe, according to that ſaying, <hi>Non audet Stygias, Pluto tentare, quod audet Perturus.</hi> The Deuill for feare doth quaking ſtand, to ſee what periury takes in hand. Yet though the crime bee neuer ſo haynous, and the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment neuer ſo grieuous, too too many care no more for falſe ſwearing and periury, then in maner of a common courteſie.</p>
               <p>I rue to thinke, that, as in duty I am bound to ſpeake; and I would to GOD,
<pb facs="tcp:173760:14"/>I might bee ſilent with ſafety: but ſeeing the burthen of duty is layd on my backe, that I muſt ſpeake againſt this horrible and rife ſinne, and ſo doe of loue, hoping for amendement: let the goodneſſe of your mindes anſwere to the greatnes of my deſire, as to looke rather to your owne duties in amending, then mine in admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing. I ſay, that publike place, and Courts of reformation, Weſtminſter Hall, and this your Honourable City, is much diſhonored and infamed with this crime and periury, though (I confeſſe) the knowne malefactors haue often receyued condigne puniſhment, for theſe ſinnes ſo offending God and equity: yet needfull is it of a continuall care to ſaue lands, liues, goods and ſoules, by graue, deepe, and diſcreet ſcrutiny.</p>
               <p>It is ſayd, there are certayne, called knights of the Poſt (I thinke ſo called for the greater part, becauſe they haue ſo much true faith, truth, and knowledge, as hath a poſt) that as one man would lend
<pb facs="tcp:173760:14"/>another an horſe to relieue his iourney; ſo will they lend another an othe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue a cauſe, preferring policy before pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and commodity before equity: they diſhonour God, to fauour men, winne themſelues wealth, with the loſſe of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and runne into this curſed and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall crime of falſe witneſſe-bearing and periury, which is the ſlaughter of ſanctity, maſſacre of verity, ſtab of equity, bane of innocency, murder of authority, and Hagge of all improbity; helles ſacring, heauens vnhallowing; Gods defiling, mans forlorning, and the worldes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twyning.</p>
               <p>Oh, that prophane and wicked wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches would be thinke themſelues, firſt, before whome they ſtand: let them but imagine it to bee before ſome man of great authority, worthy of reuerence, full of ſeuerity, and pearcing of iudgement. Secondly, that they would perſwade themſelues, when they are to giue in their teſtimony, that then was the laſt period
<pb facs="tcp:173760:15"/>of their life: and therefore then ſo to ſpeake, as one that was preſently before Gods tribunall ſeate, then for the ſame to giue an acount. And laſtly, that they would haue God before their eyes, as if he were preſent, viſibly and corporally, (as in trueth hee is inuiſibly in all places, eſpecially in that place, where God is ſayd <hi>to bee amongſt the gods.</hi>) And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to ſpeake the trueth, the whole trueth, and nothing but the trueth (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their charge) looking to God the Searcher of all thoughts, that ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth there, as witneſſe and Iudge, to allow, or diſprooue, to iudge, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite them: then would they haue one eye to God, and the other to the cauſe in queſtion; then would they iuſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the trueth in euery mans cauſe, and not make account of any mans perſon, knowing that God is Author of trueth, and therefore hateth lyes; and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill father of lyes, and therefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth trueth; that nature hath ioyned their
<pb facs="tcp:173760:15"/>tongues and hearts together, becauſe the tongue ſhould expreſse what the heart doeth thinke; that leaſings are the moſt dangerous enemies to quietneſse, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of debate; that it breaketh, and in time taketh away all the affiance and truſt that ſhould be betweene man and man; it impayreth their credit, woundeth their conſcience, &amp; ingageth their ſoules.</p>
               <p>O remember this, yee that forget God, and are poſſeſſed with whole Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of lying deuils, that make no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of a ſacred othe: feare not the diſpleaſure of men, but feare to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe the commaundements of God: reueyle not one part, to gall an enemy, nor conceyle an other part, to pleaſure a friend; ſpeake the trueth, and the whole trueth. <hi>Veritat is ſimulatio, abnegatio, &amp;c.</hi> ſayth <hi>Fulgentius.</hi> Halt not on both ſides, with one part of the teſtimony; on one part to pleaſure the Playntife, and the other, to pleaſe the Defendant. Couer not <hi>Neroes</hi> cruelty, (beware of ſcarlet
<pb facs="tcp:173760:16"/>ſinnes) vnder <hi>Catoes</hi> grauity; nor <hi>Herods</hi> butchery, with <hi>Iohn Baptiſts</hi> ſimplicity. <hi>Mala conſcientia delictorum, teſtis, Iudex, carcer, tortur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Remember, that CHRIST doeth intitle himſelfe, <hi>The faythfull and true wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse,</hi> in whoſe heart was neuer vntrue thought, in whoſe mouth was neuer guilefull word, in whoſe hands was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer falſe deed: for hee was the Way, the Trueth, and the Life; the Way, neuer erring; the Trueth, neuer fayling; the Life, euerlaſting: true in all his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, true in all his prophecies, true, in giuing vs true liberty. If then you be true by this example in heart, true in tongue, true in hand, faithfull and true witneſſes, your thoughts ſhall yeelde comfort to your ſelues, your tongues prayſes to your God; your hands, good deeds to your brethren. But if you lye without feare, you ſhall dye without GOD: and when your body is without life, your ſoule ſhall be without hope.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:173760:16"/>
               <p> And yee, moſt prudent and learned Iudges of the Land, to whome it doeth belong; though I may ſay, Ye graue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as ſometimes <hi>Bernard</hi> did to <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genius, conſid. lib. 2. Non est meae humilitatis dictare vobis, Vel ſic, vel ſic faciendum:</hi> In all humility for IESVS CHRIST his ſake, I beſeech you to reſpect of what Religion and honeſty the witneſſes bee, that are produced before you; for <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> rule doeth hold: <hi>They cannot be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to men, that are faythleſſe to God.</hi> You will not ſuffer them to robbe men by the high way ſide; much leſſe, to robbe God of his honour, the lawes of true Iuſtice, and their neighbours of their rights, liues, lands, and goods. They muſt not murder others; and ſhall they ſlay their owne ſoules? They may not ſpeake trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt their Prince; and ſhall they vtter blaſphemy againſt GOD? Why ſhould any man abuſe his owne horſe or houſe? for if they pleaſe not one, they may pleaſure another. And why ſhould any
<pb facs="tcp:173760:17"/>man bee permitted (as farre as it may bee preuented) to abuſe his owne ſoule? they are not their owne, but are bought with the precious bloud of the immaculate Lambe, Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p>I am of opinion, if I ſee one ready to drowne himſelfe, and ſtay him not, if I may, if ſo hee doeth periſh, that I am guilty of his death. But <hi>Pauca ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pienti.</hi> Thankes to God, for your reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious care already had vpon this poynt; and God graunt your perſeuerance, to the glory of God, and furtherance of iuſtice.</p>
               <p>And thus much for theſe words in Chriſtes ſecond title, <hi>The faythfull and true witneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:173760:17"/>
               <head>That beginning of the creatures of God.</head>
               <p>CHriſt is ſayd to be the Author and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginner of the creatures of God, two maner of wayes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, as it is <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.3. <hi>All things were made by it, and without it was made nothing that was made.</hi> So that he is beginning without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning: for he that giueth beginning to all things, muſt needs haue none himſelfe: hee that is before all things, cannot after be made to be: he that created all other, cannot himſelf be a creature: he that ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and giueth Being to all, muſt needs be himſelfe an eternall and infinite Being, which neuer began to be, nor neuer ſhall make an end to be. Therefore he is not the beginning amongſt creatures, that is, the firſt amongſt creatures that began to be, but the beginning, that is, the Beginner &amp; Former of all things whatſoeuer be.</p>
               <p>This Maieſty of God in the creation, not a little ſetteth forth the dignity of the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage: for how materially ſhould we regard his pleaſure, that is Prince of all power,
<pb facs="tcp:173760:18"/>who as hee made vs of nought, ſo can hee bring vs to nought; and can make vs heires of heauen, or firebrands of hell.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he is ſaid to be the beginning of the creatures of God, as hee is in this ſence, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4. <hi>As he hath choſen vs in him, before the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation of the world, that we ſhould be holy, and without blame before him in loue, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. The Apoſtle affirmeth, that <hi>God hath from the beginning choſen them to ſaluation, through ſanctification of the ſpirit, and the fayth of truth, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereby we may ſee, God looked on the countenance of Chriſt, when hee firſt made man, that whereas in <hi>Adam</hi> we all periſhed, ſo wee ſhould in Chriſt all be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired: and this was his eternall decree from the beginning. Therefore is he ſayd to be the Lambe ſlain from the beginning, and Ieſus Chriſt, yeſterday and to day, and the ſame for euer.</p>
               <p>Now, as Chriſt is ſayd to be the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the creatures of God, two maner of wayes, ſo is the creature to be conſidered
<pb facs="tcp:173760:18"/>two maner of wayes: that is, not onely by creation, but by renouation, as it is implied <hi>Pſa.</hi> 51.10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.15. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10. Whereby it appeareth, that mans laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing is as great a worke of God, and as mighty as the firſt.</p>
               <p>In the firſt creation, <hi>Adam</hi> of nothing was made good. In the ſecond, man was of ill made good. Now to draw one contrary out of another, is of no leſſe diuine power then to make good of nothing: for in ill is a naturall hatred and reſiſtance to be made good, but in nothing is no reſiſtance, <hi>Aug. Par ſit vtriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> poteſtas, &amp; iuſtos creare, &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pios iuſtificare:</hi> yet muſt the latter bee of more mercy then the firſt. The firſt was of the earth, earthy, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.47. And by this creation, not only the earthy, that is to ſay, the corruptible nature, which doth onely ſauour terrene and earthly things, is made diuine, hauing in this life the heart made heauenly, with diuine faith, the conſcience heauenly, with diuine peace, the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding heauenly, with diuine knowledge, the affections heauenly, with diuine loue,
<pb facs="tcp:173760:19"/>the life heauenly, with diuine works; but being thus prepared in this life preſent, ſhall in the bleſſed heauens, of wretched, be made bleſſed; of maymed, be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; of ſtayned, be made pure; of caducall, immortall; and of corruptible, eternall.</p>
               <p>So in the like maner, in the firſt was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated in the humane body, being, life, and ſence; and in the humane ſoule, reaſon, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory and wil: But ſuch a being, as without this laſt renouation, better not to be, being indeed nothing elſe but a perpetuall lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing; ſuch a life, as was and is to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued; ſuch ſence, as was and is to bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed; ſuch reaſon, as was and is to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued; ſuch will, as was and is to be diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; ſuch memory, as hath often fayled. But in this ſecond is not onely a being, but a happy being; not life alone, but eternity; not only ſence, but iocundity; reaſon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out obſcuring, wil without diſturbing; and memory without forgetting.</p>
               <p>So in the firſt, the body was drawne out of duſt, life out of breath, ſence out of life, mortality out of nature, and miſery out of
<pb facs="tcp:173760:19"/>ſinne. But in this ſecond, both body and ſoule are drawne out of hell, life out of death, and ſence out of torment, eternity out of mortality, and felicity out of miſery.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, in the firſt (as we muſt thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully confeſſe) though man was moſt roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and magnificently ſeated, and made Lord of this inferiour world, had Paradiſe for his Palace, all creatures to ſerue him, all treaſures to enrich him, all elements to help him, the earth to ſuſtain him, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to conſerue him: yet in this ſecond (my heart doth melt to thinke it: O won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull thing!) mortall man is made heire of the immortall God, and ſucceedeth in the inheritance of his vnmeaſurable glory, hath heauen for his folace, Angels to helpe him, Gods ſpirit to ſuſtayne him, his grace to enrich him, Gods Sonne to redeeme him, God himſelfe to adorne him.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, God made man at the firſt, when he was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the earth is now, ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe without feeling, and liueleſſe without mouing; ſo that if he had no praiſe of well doing, hee had no blame of ill deſeruing.
<pb facs="tcp:173760:20"/>But now at the laſt, when man had fallen from the God of life, into the power of the king of death; and in preferring the credit of the lying Deuill, before the truth of the liuing God, had not onely rendred diſobedience for duty, and great vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes for Gods great bounty; but alſo had ſence of feeling, and torments for euer abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: then the gracious and bountifull God, to ſhew not onely a patience in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, compaſſion in pittying, a mercy in pardoning; but alſo a loue in retayning, a bounty in reſtoring, a magnificence in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging his eſtate againe, doeth argue his loue to haue ſo much the more exceeded, in how much mans loue had the leſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. <hi>Opus ſine exemplo, gratia ſine merito, charitas ſine modo,</hi> ſayth <hi>Bernard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, the firſt creation was made by the might of Gods Sonne; but the ſecond by the death of Gods Sonne: ſo God la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored to make the firſt, but Chriſt ſuffered to make the laſt: ſo that in the firſt, man was exalted; but in the laſt, God was debaſed, &amp; that ſo interchangeably, as that by how
<pb facs="tcp:173760:20"/>much the Sonne of God was humbled, in ſo much was the ſonne of man aduanced: for God came downe to earth, and man went vp to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: God took our humane fleſh, and man his diuine ſpirit: God was made the ſonne of man, &amp; man was made the ſonne of God: yea God was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; man was acquited; Chriſt ſuffered, and man was redeemed; he was done to bitter death, and man receyued to eternall life; he ſuſtayned the paynes of hell, and man poſſeſſed the ioyes of heauen; he was crowned with pricks &amp; thornes, to crowne man the King of bliſſe. Thus was God depreſſed to mans miſery, and man exalted to Gods glory.</p>
               <p>Now, what greater loue could God ſhew to man, then to preferre man to the glory of God? and yet in doing it, by detruding himſelfe to our miſery, he doth double the bounty by ſuffering, which he beſtowed in aduauncing: for in giuing his glory, what ſoeuer he had, he gaue him all: But in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our miſery, he freely gaue himſelfe and all. Now if we can neuer ſatiſfie for the
<pb facs="tcp:173760:21"/>greatnes of that glory, what ſhal we render for this his vnmeaſureable loue?</p>
               <p>Thus then to conclude, was the Sonne of God by the firſt, our beginning of life; but in the ſecond hee brought vs an end of death by the firſt, mold was made a man; by the ſecond, ſinne was made a Saint: the firſt made man the image of God; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, the ſonne of God: by the firſt, was made a humane ſoule; by the ſecond, a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſpirit: by the one, he is made Lord of earth; by the ſecond, King of heauen: by this he hath a world full of creatures; by that he hath an heauen full of ioyes: ſo, by the one he is wonderfully created, by the other ineſtimably redeemed: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Sonne of God declared by the firſt his vnmeaſurable greatnes, by the laſt, his incomparable goodnes.</p>
               <p>Loe, behold here, Beloued, what won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful great things the Lord hath done for vs: we ought (if it were poſſible) to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable in all kindnes and thankfulnes to his great loue and goodnes: which thing, ſince wee cannot poſsibly performe, yet,
<pb facs="tcp:173760:21"/>when we haue done all that we are able, we muſt of neceſſity confeſſe wee haue done much leſſe then we ought: how ought we notwithſtanding to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tend to do all things to the vttermoſt of our power, that by our readines in doing that which we can, wee ſhew our willingneſſe, that we would doe that as we cannot: where, if it be ſo, we do far leſſe then our duty, euen when we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to do more then our power: what duty doe they performe, who when they ſhould doe more then all, performe leſſe then nothing? nay not onely ſeeke not to aduaunce any duety, but ſhame not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite ſo great goodnes with all impiety, by falſhood, fraud, and periury, ſeeking onely to anger &amp; moſt grieuouſly to offend him, which hath moſt egregiouſly deſerued of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But if it be a ſauage and brutiſh thing for a man ſo to behaue himſelfe, as to be (I ſay) not onely vnworthy, but vanquiſhed of a good turne; how monſtrous &amp; prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious a thing is it, to render immeaſurable wickedneſſe, for incomparable goodneſſe, and that eſpecially to Gods eternall Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty?
<pb facs="tcp:173760:22"/>And if we ſhould not ſuffer our good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to be ouercom by others wickednes, as the Apoſtle ſayth, how incredible obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate are we, if our wickednes cannot be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercom by Gods mighty diuine goodnes? We are to know, bleſſed Brethren, that the Lord hath not placed vs therefore in this world, that we ſhould by ſauage vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes become worſe then brute beaſts, but that as humane creatures, we ſhould excel in all humanity, and ſhew our great loue towards him, for his great loue towards vs, acknowledging our gratefulnes for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruednes, and with all our might honour him, that doth with all his bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ties pleaſure vs. Wherefore let vs learne by the pattern of his vvorthyneſſe, to be made like to his goodneſſe, becauſe hee hath promiſed vs in Chriſt, that they vvhich are like vnto him in grace, ſhould raigne vvith him in glory.</p>
               <p>And thus we are aſſured of, that, looke what is in Chriſt promiſed, becauſe he is God <hi>Amen,</hi> ſhall bee performed vndou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly. Which thing that the Lord may
<pb facs="tcp:173760:22"/>effectually doe indeed, let vs with all our hearts beſeech him to bleſſe vs, that wee may with all our hearts ſerue him, that after this life preſent, wee may with him eternally enioy the life to come: which God graunt for his Chriſt his ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:173760:23"/>
            <head>The ſecond part.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Reue. 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="15">15 I know thy works, that thou art neyther cold nor hote, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="16">16 Therefore, becauſe thou art luke-warme, and neyther cold nor hote, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="17">17 For thou ſayeſt I am rich &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Lord Ieſus, hauing before premiſed the deſcription of his dreadfull Maieſty, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of his infallible knowledge which cannot be deceiued; of his immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble truth, which cannot be changed; of his inuiolable faythfulnes, which cannot be corrupted: Hauing thus (I ſay) premitted (as a thunderbolt) the excellency of his nature, he proceedeth to note downe the faultineſſe of their behauiour, giuing them to conceyue thereby, that it is in vayne to make falſe ſemblance with God: For by reaſon of his infallibleneſſe, he will not be deceyued by them; &amp; becauſe of his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes,
<pb facs="tcp:173760:23"/>he will not deceiue them. But as by vertue of his knowledge, hee ſeeth what they are: ſo for his inuiolablenes, hee will vſe them as they are: aſsured they may be, whatſoeuer he promiſeth, becauſe hee is true, hee aſſuredly performeth, becauſe he is faythfull.</p>
            <p>The Laodicians being thus aſſured to find reward according to their deſert, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to declare; both what they haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, and how they ſhall be rewarded. Wherein the Lord ſetteth downe to them, Firſt, the cryme. Secondly, the cauſe of the cryme. Thirdly, the puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the crime is, to be neither hote nor cold. Secondly, the cauſe, worldly riche; and ſpirituall pouerty. Thirdly, the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, to be vomited out of the Lords mouth.</p>
            <p>The grieuouſnes of this crime we ſhall the more euidently perceiue, when wee marke throughly, firſt, who they are that are hote. Secondly, who they are that are cold. Thirdly, and conſequently, a third ſort, Neuters, that are neyther hote nor colde.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173760:24"/>
            <p> They are hote in Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whom Chriſt baptizeth <hi>cum Spiritu ſancto &amp; igni:</hi> for ſo were the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. when the holy Ghoſt ſate in fiery clouen toungs on euery one of them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in fiery tongues, to make them lucent and ardent. Secondly, in tongues, to make them prudent &amp; cloquent. Thirdly, theſe tongues were clouen, to ſhew, that as euery tongue was made many by clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing: ſo ſhould they haue diuerſity of gifts and multiplicity of languages, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6. And as one ſayth, <hi>Omnium gentium linguas loquitur Eccleſia.</hi> For as in fire there are many notable qualities perceptable to the ſences, as clearenes, beauty, burning, heat, dryneſſe, and many ſingular effects anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable therevnto, as to make pure, adorne, manifeſt, ſeparate and conſume: So this alluding of the holy Ghoſt vnto fire, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs in mind, that Gods ſpirit worketh like fire, in the Saints, an illuſtrious bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; yet not of the eyes, but of the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; cleareneſſe, not of colour, but of conſcience; heat, not of fire, but of zeale;
<pb facs="tcp:173760:24"/>and a thirſt &amp; drynes, not vnto moyſture, but vnto goodnes, making men to ſhine in the darknes of this world, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.5. to be adorned with the beauty of holineſſe, as the world with the beauty of heauen, and to be made pure in heart through fayth, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. as fire doth purify gold; to bee zealous and feruent in ſpirit, as the fire makes men feruent in heat, <hi>Ro.</hi> 12. to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume our corrupt affections as droſſe with flame, <hi>Ro.</hi> 8. to fill vs as full with the fruits of righteouſnes, as fruit trees are filled with the fruit of the Sunne, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.11.</p>
            <p>So that by means of this ſacred fire, the Saints are made with zeale, like S. <hi>Ioh. Bap.</hi> burning fyrebrands; through loue, like the Apoſtles, ſhining lights; through faith, like the wiſe virgins, ſhining lamps; through grace, like the righteous in heauens king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, euer-ſhining ſtarres. And no maruel; for theſe haue not only caſt off the works of darknes, by mortifying their own fleſh, denying their owne ſelues, ſubduing their owne wils, forgoing their owne delights, &amp; by contemning the glory of the world,
<pb facs="tcp:173760:25"/>the flatterings of proſperity, &amp; the deſpites of aduerſity; but are made infatigable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all labours, intrepidable againſt all dangers, inuincible againſt all pleaſures, and inexpugnable againſt all power; and haue moreouer, after a moſt diuine and heauenly maner, put on the armour of light, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12. and walke in the light, vſing (as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſayth) <hi>Tanta humilitate in conuerſatione, ſtabilitate in fide, veritate in verbis, in factis iustitia:</hi> ſuch gouernment in maners, and iuſtice in workes, as that their whole liues are nothing elſe, but ſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacles of piety; their bodies, tabernacles of ſanctity; their mouthes, oracles of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; their hearts, habitacles of charity; and themſelues, mirrours &amp; miracles of all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity. And they that are ſuch, may right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſayd to be hote in Religion.</p>
            <p>Behold (beloued) how greatly ought we to be inflamed with the loue of this Excellency, as alſo confounded with the ſhame of our indignity, that the more farre wee are off from the worthineſſe of the Saints, the more we ought to endeuour to
<pb facs="tcp:173760:25"/>come neere vnto the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now, by the contrary to thoſe that are hote, wee may eaſily diſcerne what theſe are that are cold: that is, ſuch as haue no ſparke of this heauenly fire, no heate, nor comfort of the holy Spirit, being without light in darkeneſſe; cold without loue, and impure without goodnes; &amp; therfore ſuch as the holy Ghoſt noteth, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. <hi>as are not waſhed, as are not ſanctified, as are not iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the Name of the Lord Ieſus, and by the Spirit of our God:</hi> ſuch as <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.12. are ſayd to bee <hi>without Christ;</hi> ſuch as hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth, in the firſt to the Corinthians, the ſixt Chapter, <hi>to be Idolaters and adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereby we may gather, three ſorts of theſe <hi>Pſukroi,</hi> key-cold in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; Atheiſts, naturall men, and Epicures. The Atheiſt, the Apoſtle deſcribeth, to be without God; the naturall man, without Chriſt; the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, without any ſparke of the bleſſed Spirit: becauſe the Atheiſt wants the light of nature, <hi>Ro.</hi> 1.20, 21. the naturall man, the light of grace, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. the Epicure,
<pb facs="tcp:173760:26"/>the light of the law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. For the Atheiſt, becauſe his hart is darkned ſaith the Apoſt. <hi>Ro.</hi> 1.21. <hi>When they knew God glorified him not as God.</hi> The naturall man, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he wanteth the ſpirit of grace, cannot know the things that are of God: for as no man knoweth the things of man, but the ſpirit of man that is in him; ſo the things of God, knoweth no man, but the ſpirit of God. And the Epicure, becauſe he regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not to know God, according to the law of God, God giueth him vp to a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate mind, to do the things that are not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient. Whereby it comes to paſſe, that the Atheiſt becomes irreligious without hope; the naturall man, erronious without truth; and the Epicure, impious without conſcience. The Atheiſt, in middeſt of light, remayneth ſtill in darknes: the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall man, in time of trueth, in errour; and the Epicure, in time of grace, liueth ſtill in ſinne. The Atheiſt, in ſtead of God, hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his owne will; the naturall man, the Idols of his owne heart; the Epicure, his paunch, and his owne pleaſure.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173760:26"/>
            <p> And thus the Atheiſt, becauſe he is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out light, and without hope, is cold in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: the naturall man, becauſe hee is without Chriſt, without grace, without truth: the Epicure, becauſe he is careleſſe without feare, ſhameles without honeſty, and ſenceles without conſcience: which are men (to vſe the words of <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>Iude</hi>) for all inanity of goodnes, as wels without water; for inſtability &amp; lightnes, as winds without rayne; for defilings and filthineſſe, ſpots without clenſing; for fruitles barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, trees without fruite; Starres without light, for darknes; fleſh without ſpirit, for ſenſualneſſe; beaſtes without reaſon, for brutiſhnes; and men without God, for prophaneneſſe.</p>
            <p>Then woe be to vs, if wee be without Religion, &amp; liue as miſcreants in the midſt of Saints, and to the corruption of nature, doe adde the contempt of grace.</p>
            <p>But now to come to our Neuters (the thing we ſeeke after) we may eaſily gather by the negation of theſe two, that are in ſuch wiſe hote, and in ſuch wiſe cold, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſpoken,
<pb facs="tcp:173760:27"/>what he is, that in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hote nor cold,</hi> and partly, how by parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of both, he is neyther of both: for he that neither hath the comfort of the holy Ghoſt, in ſuch degree as a Saint, nor is ſo chill with the coldneſſe of iniquity, as an Infidell, is <hi>Neuter,</hi> that is, neither Saint, nor Infidell: but as betwixt a Horſe and an Aſſe, is procreated a Mule; betwixt a Lion and a Woolfe, an Hyena: ſo betwixt this heat, and that coldnes, is ingendred a <hi>Nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidian</hi> of prophaneſſe, which is neither hote nor cold: not cold, becauſe hee doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to know God: not hote, becauſe hee doth in workes deny God, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. not cold, becauſe hee doth appeare righteous before men: not hote, becauſe he is full of iniquity before God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.13. not cold, becauſe hee doth worſhip God with his lips: not hote, becauſe he is farre from him with his heart, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.8. not cold, becauſe he loueth in word &amp; in tongue: not hote, becauſe hee doth not loue in deed and in truth, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.18. ſo that he is holy in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, but hollow in conuerſation; of a
<pb facs="tcp:173760:27"/>good opinion touching truth, but of an ill exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple touching life: ſuch a one indeed, as doth hold Religion, but yet without zeale; as will ſay, he is of the true Religion, but is not truly religious; as hath knowledge, but without loue; as profeſſeth the fayth, but without workes, <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.14. This is the crue of that ſurlike company, that pretend co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, but without feeling, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. they are come to that poynt of inſenſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſinne, that they ſhame not to ſin with delight; ſuch as haue a deſire, but without all performing. And as by the negation, the luke-warme Chriſtian is a Neuter; ſo is he by participation an <hi>Ambodexter.</hi> Theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue their coats made of Linſy wolſey: theſe are they that plowe with an Oxe &amp; an Aſſe: theſe doe ſow their land with diuers kind of ſeeds: theſe are like the Griffin in the war between the birds, &amp; the beaſts: to the birds, he ſhewed his wings; to the beaſts, his feet, profeſſing ayd to both, yet ſhew'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe Neuter to both: hauing, by reaſon of this partaking of both natures, a naturall facility to playe with both hands, being
<pb facs="tcp:173760:28"/>ready both to worſhip <hi>Baal,</hi> with <hi>Achab,</hi> and the Lord with <hi>Iehu,</hi> 1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 16. &amp; 29. both to build vp the Temple with <hi>Zerub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel,</hi> and pull it down with the Aramites, <hi>Ezr.</hi> 4. to bleſſe for Iſrael, and curſe for <hi>Balak, Num.</hi> 24. to cry <hi>Hoſanna</hi> to day, and <hi>Crucifige</hi> to morrow, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. &amp; 27. <hi>Partim ſeruiunt Deo, partim Diabolo,</hi> ſayth <hi>Aug.</hi> where God being angry the deuill ſhould haue any part, doth leaue his part, and let the deuill take all: for by reaſon he hath his heauenly heat delayed with worldly cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, he is not feruent in any religion, a man indifferent for all religions, ready to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take any religion, but indeed, a louer of no religion: for that he is alwayes for his two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold mixtures, mungrell-minded; for want of heate, cold affected; through warme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, buſy-headed; by negation, hollow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted; with partaking, double-handed; by delaying, halfe addicted; in euery muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſooneſt changed: ſo that as luke-warme water will be ſooneſt yce; ſo luke-warme men wil be ſooneſt wicked: &amp; as yce wil ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſſolue, then admit warmnes, ſo they
<pb facs="tcp:173760:28"/>as eaſily dye, as returne to goodneſſe. For which cauſe, Chriſt auoucheth in this place, not onely the misbeleeuing Infidell, but the prophane Atheiſt to be better, or not ſo bad, as the luke-warme Neuter; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Atheiſt profeſſeth to be as he is, openly wicked; the Neuter, by ill diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, to be good, whereby that ill doeth more annoy vnder colour of goodneſſe. The Atheiſt thinks not there is a God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he thinketh he is not. The Neuter thinketh there is a God, but regardeth him not (An erring by darknes of nature, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times being inlightned, doth hunger after grace) The Neuter inlightned already with the good gifts of grace, through ſatiety, ofttimes returneth to the vomit of nature: ſo, whereas the one ſort is a committer of wickednes, the other is beſides an abuſer of godlineſſe; the one offending through boldnes of ignorance, the other through peruerſnes of will; thoſe, through frailty of nature; theſe, through conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of grace.</p>
            <p>Whereby it is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that all luke-warme Chriſtians, are for al prophane behauiour,
<pb facs="tcp:173760:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:173760:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:173760:30"/>moſt notable hypocrites, moſt diſſembling <hi>Ambo-dexters;</hi> in dealing with men, <hi>Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters;</hi> in partaking with neither, <hi>Nulli-fidians;</hi> in relapſing from both, counterfets of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to profane vertue, Apoſtataes from God, full of all wickednes, for all kind of vice, monſters in nature, Atheiſts in errour, Epicures in pleaſure, Saints in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and deuils in demeanour.</p>
            <p>What wonder then, if the Lord will haue no coldneſſe in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that profeſſe him, when as in onely warmnes there doe muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch an army, and lyeth hid ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous an Ambuſcado of wickednes?</p>
            <p>The more ſhameful that any fault is, the more carefull ſhould we be to ſhun it. And what can bee more haynous, then ſuch a crime? and yet what more common, then ſuch behauiour? It is an olde ſaying, <hi>Non omnes Sancti, qui calcant limina Templi.</hi> All that gloweth, is not gold, nor all that ſeem, are not Saints. We profeſſe the Kingdom of the Goſpell: but for the moſt part, wee imbrace the kingdome of the world; wee beleeue like Chriſtians, &amp; liue like Pagans;
<pb facs="tcp:173760:30"/>looke like the Lambe, and ſpeake like the Dragon; the Name of God is in our tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, but the feare of God is not in our hearts: we can ſerue all turnes, change our ſelues into all formes, and with a trice become openly Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, ſecretly Papiſts; inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neyther, outwardly both; Saints in face, ſerpents in heart; Angels in ſhew, Diuels in deed; Gods word ſwimming in our lips, but deteſtable Satan digging in our ſoules.</p>
            <p>There was neuer better teaching, nor worſe following; more talking, and leſſe practizing: not like <hi>Pambo,</hi> who, when he had heard one leſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, would learne no more, before he would practiſe that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for we will heare any thing, but frame our ſelues to follow nothing; finde great fault with our former ſinnes, and obiect, our forefathers liued in ignorance, (and in trueth, they knew very little, but did very much; they were ſpare in ſpeach, &amp; noble in acts:) but we, as though degenerate, or none of their children, nay rather, none of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the more good wee knowe, the leſſe good we doe; we haue filed tongues, but defiled hearts.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173760:31"/>
            <p> Now, if all the world would ſet to their hands, to defend vs from ruine, yet howe can God ſuffer that Common-wealth to ſtand, that ſhrowdeth ſuch a multitude of wickednes, vnder the ſacred holines of his moſt bleſſed Name? Wherefore (deare Citizens) let vs repent with Niniue, that we be not caſt away with Laodicea. And thus much touching the crime.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>NOw to ſpeake of the cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord, in this place, aſſigneth two cauſes, why the loue of Religion is quay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Laodiceans; and they may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned as cauſes this day, why it alſo quay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in vs.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>worldly riches.</hi> Secondly, <hi>ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all pouerty:</hi> the one oftentimes enſuing the other: for men vnmeaſureably rich, are commonly immoderately bent vpon the world; ſo incumbred with the toyle of worldly cares, that they can ſcarſly reſpite themſelues one breath or gaſpe of an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly thought; or elſe, after the maner of theſe Loadiceans, hauing their wealth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, begin to conceyue ſo well of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,
<pb facs="tcp:173760:31"/>that they thinke all to be well, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they doe; and becauſe they haue goods inow, thinke themſelues to be good inough, cenſuring after the iudgement of the world, that God doeth fauour, whom the world doeth proſper: and therefore, becauſe they are well, touching the worlds proſperity, they deeme themſelues well alſo, touching Gods fauour. For proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity is often proud, wealth wanton, and many times, not onely wilful, but alſo wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe too. <hi>The rich man is wiſe in his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyt</hi> (ſayth <hi>Salomon.</hi>) As who would ſay, he were in deed but a foole.</p>
            <p>Lo, how riches can inchaunt the mind, to cauſe a man to think himſelfe wiſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is but fooliſh; ſtrong, when hee is but weake; fenced, when he is naked; godly, when he is wicked; and to leaue the Lord, the Tower and ſtrength of his defence, to truſt in the weak &amp; rotten wals of wealth. For the nature of man being compoſed of two contraries, of a mortall body, the earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. and an eternall ſoule, which is from heauen, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12. &amp; are as contrary,
<pb facs="tcp:173760:32"/>as heauen and earth: whileſt either of theſe parties are naturally moued to conſerue the good eſtate of his owne nature, it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe, that both this baſe &amp; earthly part drawes a man vehemently to be attent vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earthly things; &amp; contrary, that diuine &amp; heauenly part doth couet to carry men vp into heauen, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence he is deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: By meanes of which repugnancy in mans nature, it is brought to paſſe, that man is wonderfully drawne into contrary &amp; repugnant deſires, endeuoring to ioyne things together, which of their owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are ſeuered moſt fartheſt aſunder, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying himſelfe with infinite toyle, how to ioyne God and the world together; to be partaker of corporall pleaſures, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ioyes; and poſſeſſe both all proſperity of the earth, and all felicity in heauen. And this is the cauſe of all Neutrality at this day: for we would all the ſort of vs fayne be Chriſtians and worldlings too; worſhip God and Mammon too; taſte the ſweetnes of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and of the earth too: &amp; ſo would be Neuters, that is, hote and cold too. In
<pb facs="tcp:173760:32"/>which conflict of contrary and impoſſible deſires, if that groſse &amp; carnall part get the vpper hand (as without the aſſiſtance of Gods diuine power, it muſt needs do) both becauſe of the corruptnes of our nature, as alſo that the Iewell of the ſoule lyeth wrapped vp in the body, as a folded ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, vnknowne to the outward man, that draweth away the heart from God, as the Adamant yron, to the veneration of the world, pulling him, as a bird tyed by the legge, when he would fly vp into heauen, downe againe to the earth, and ſo to fixe his affiance in the confidence of creatures, which is the cauſe, why couetous men are called Idolaters, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.5. and <hi>Coloſſians</hi> 3.15.</p>
            <p>He calleth the couetous man an Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous perſon, becauſe hee aſcribeth to his treaſure the diuine power, which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth to the diuine nature, and as a reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father ſayth, <hi>colit Idola, quae finxit:</hi> For whereas the eternall Maieſty is onely moſt mighty, wiſe, bountiful, rich, bleſſed, and full of all goodnes: euen ſo, ſayth the
<pb facs="tcp:173760:33"/>miſer, is my money, that can doe all things, therefore the moſt mighty; prouide all things, therefore moſt wiſe; giue vs all things, therefore moſt bountiful; purchaſe all things, therefore moſt rich, cauſe a man to liue in all plenty and abundance, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt bleſsed.</p>
            <p>Loe, ſo greatly doth his treaſure change his heart, as that it maketh him to cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge his God, drawing him from the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, downe right to the deuill of hell: for he it is (the deuill I meane) whome all anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity hath accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to be the god of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, whome for the ſame cauſe the Greeks called <hi>Ploutos,</hi> the Latines <hi>Dis,</hi> our Sauiour <hi>Mammon,</hi> which wee call riches, whom this rich man doeth acknowledge for his god, &amp; all the world beſides acknowledge for a deuill; not onely becauſe that gold &amp; ſiluer, which is the riches of the world, is found deepe in the earth, as it were, in the pit of hell, but becauſe mony is as mighty vnto miſchiefe, as the deuill himſelfe. It can make miracles, and worke wonders, condemne Innocents, vanquiſh armies, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome
<pb facs="tcp:173760:33"/>kingdomes; nay, the nature of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches can alter nature, cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the heart, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the will, &amp; turne the reaſonable mind into brutiſh affections, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Diuitiarum ſequela, eſt luxuria, ira intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, furor iniuſtus, arogantia ſuperba,</hi> and all brutiſh affections. No maruaile then, if an other reuerend Father ſayth, <hi>Nullu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis in illo corde veſtigium, in quo ſibi auaritia fecit habitaculum.</hi> Whereby wee may ſee, that euen as the Sonne of God came into the world in pouerty, as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the workes of the deuill; ſo doeth the deuill come into the world, to deſtroy the workes of God by riches, turning liuing creatures into Idoles, men into beaſts, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils into gods, light into darknes, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen into hel. Rightly therfore ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Ye cannot ſerue God and Mammon,</hi> ſeeing it is as impoſsible, as to ſerue God &amp; the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. Well then may that be allowed, that riches is the ſame as <hi>Pluto</hi> is, if thoſe men that ſay, I am rich, and boaſt of the rich deuill, become to bee neyther cold nor hote to poore Chriſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173760:34"/>
            <p> And this commeth not to paſſe through any iniquity that is in treaſure, but onely through the prauity of our owne nature, which doeth peruert theſe excellent crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures on to that euill, which were created for our good: for otherwiſe, riches are the bleſſings of God, <hi>Pro.</hi> 10. crowne of the wiſe, <hi>Pro.</hi> 14. fountaynes of liberality and bounty, <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>What incredible improbity is it then of our nature, which doeth through his inſection, abuſe theſe great treaſures of the world, which God hath ordayned to be bleſsings to the rich, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts to the poore, fortifications againſt iniuries, munition for defence of equity, fountaynes of libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, Almenors of charity, Diadems of wiſdome, furniſhments of bounty, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of vertue, &amp; adiuments of life, as to make them bayts of perdition, aliments of pleaſure, enſignes of pride, weapons of reuenge, armour vnto ſtrife, and finally, the ſeruants vnto all ſeruile vſes, &amp; ſoueraignes of all ſeruile minds?</p>
            <p>Wherefore (my beloued Brethren)
<pb facs="tcp:173760:34"/>ſeeing the vſe of riches is ſo dangerous, our nature ſo pernicious, the abuſe ſo impious, alas, why ſhould we with ſuch vnmeaſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able greedineſſe gape after riches, which not onely, as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſayth, <hi>poſſeſsa onerant, amata inquinant, amiſſa cruciant:</hi> are bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens to them that poſſeſse them, defilings to them that loue them, and torments to them that loſe them: but chiefly, becauſe they inchaunt &amp; bewitch vs to the world, extinguiſh and quench our zeale in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and mightily hale vs and driue vs away from God, to eternall perdition?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>NOw, there is an other ſort of riches,</hi> which our Sauiour affirmeth to be in deed &amp; truth, pouerty, a counterfet kind of wealth, paynted fire, and yet is in ſhew ſo good, as nothing can be better; but in proofe ſo ill, as nothing can be worſe: it is taken for the ineſtimable price of heauen, but is not worth a deſpicable mite of the earth: that is, <hi>Humane merites, and Iuſticiaries workes,</hi> which ſeeme to be golden vertues, but are in deed ſhining ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Theſe merit-mongers, our Sauiour
<pb facs="tcp:173760:35"/>elegantly deciphers vnder the name of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, becauſe, euen as worldlings boaſt of their wealth, ſo hypocrits of works; as they ſay, I am rich, ſo theſe ſay, I am righteous; as they put confidence in money, ſo theſe in merits; as they thinke to make friends of their Mammon of iniquity, ſo theſe to win fauour by their holineſſe and ſanctity; the one thinks to haue all, that is to be had in earth; and the other, to want nothing that may bee purchaſed in heauen. By reaſon whereof, in theſe merits, our Sauiour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth three properties.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that in the world they goe for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant goods. Secondly, that they are moſt pernicious ills. Thirdly, that in ſeeming good, they are the more euill, becauſe the ſeeming deceyueth, while it annoyeth.</p>
            <p>Now, that in the world they goe for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant goods, hee proueth by the mouth of the very owner, who knoweth beſt to ſet his owne price vpon his owne wares, and he himſelfe ſaith, <hi>I am rich, &amp; want nothing,</hi> that might ſeeme to purchaſe heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſelfe. I haue kept the Lawe of God: I haue not
<pb facs="tcp:173760:35"/>murdered, ſtolen, committed adultery, &amp;c. and if I had offended, yet I haue workes inow to ſatisfy for ſinne: for ſatiſfaction, as Saint <hi>Tho. in Quaeſt. deſatiſf. poſsib.</hi> 13. <hi>eſt, cum paena culpae aequatur:</hi> and iuſtice, ſayth hee, or a iuſt mends, is but <hi>contra paſſum,</hi> that is, whereas on the one ſide, I haue taken pleaſure in offending, I ſhould on the other ſide <hi>contra pati,</hi> ſuffer as much griefe in repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting. And I ſay, the Iuſticiaries haue alwaies done this; for I neuer took ſo much pleaſure in ſinne, but I haue taken as great ſorrow in penance; I haue faſted twice a weeke, &amp;c. yea, I faſt when others feaſt; this body of mine hath bin chaſtiſed with whips, when others are pampered with cates; I haue giuen my goods to the poore, and my lands to build Abbeyes: and, if he be rich, <hi>non qui plus habet, ſed qui minus cupit,</hi> then I, not onely, becauſe I haue a great treaſure of good works, but alſo am ſatiſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in deſire, may be iuſtly counted to bee rich indeed. And thus you ſee how hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane merits goe for currant goods.</p>
            <p>But whileſt they aduaunce their merits
<pb facs="tcp:173760:36"/>to ſo high a rate, they make the price of heanen indeed to be but little worth: for as <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. they that go about to eſtabliſh their owne righteouſnes, doe not ſubmit themſelues to the righteouſnes of God: for while they are pure in their own eyes, they haue no care at all to be waſhed from their filthineſſe, <hi>Pro.</hi> 30.12. ſo that they are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tain of purity, which is opened to the houſe of <hi>Dauid, Zach.</hi> 13.1. &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the white robes of righteouſnes, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the bloud of the Lambe, <hi>Reu.</hi> 8. &amp; without the cleare criſtall riuers of grace, that flow fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſanctuary of God, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 47. ſo that albeit they be adorned neuer ſo royally with the beauty of good works, yet are they without that wedding garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of fayth, and true holineſſe, wherewith the newe Ieruſalem was trimmed, as a Bride that came down out of heauen from God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. <hi>Reu.</hi> 21. and finally, without all the true treaſure, which is the ineſtimable riches of Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.8. and therefore indeed are extremely poore.</p>
            <p>Whereby appeareth, what a pernicious
<pb facs="tcp:173760:36"/>euill merits are, that whereas it is the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall worke of God to iuſtify ſinners, and to ſaue the miſerable and damned, and hath therefore ordayned the Law, as a glaſſe, to ſhew men the corruption of themſelues, by the pureneſſe of the Law, that knowing their owne ſinfull nature, they may bee ſchooled to ſeeke to Chriſt for grace, theſe men will not ſuffer God to performe his owne naturall worke, becauſe they wil not ſuffer themſelues to become ſinners, nor acknowledge their owne miſerable eſtate: whereby it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe, that by ſeeking through merits to fulfill the law, they grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly tranſgreſſe againſt the Law, and in ſtead of obedience, ſhew rebellion: for the law going about to proue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinners, <hi>Ro.</hi> 3.23. they do thereby contrary to the law, proue themſelues to be Saints; it bringeth them to the knowledge of ſinne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7. thei gather out the righteouſnes of works; it humbleth them to Gods mercy, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.23. they pranke themſelues in their own iuſtice: by meanes whereof, in ſtead of humility, they gather pride; in ſtead of
<pb facs="tcp:173760:37"/>grace, merits; in ſtead of mercy, wrath; and ſo conſequently, for truth, errour; for life, death; for heauen, hel. And thus, according to that notable prediction of the Prophet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69. <hi>Their owne table is made their owne ſnare,</hi> that is, the law, which is the table of al their wiſdome &amp; vnderſtanding, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.6. whileſt they looke to that they falſly haue, rather then to that they truly want, it is made a ſnare to intangle them in all igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and errour.</p>
            <p>Can there be a more greater ill deuiſed, then merits are, which doe not onely that which is exceeding euil, that is, draw men into perdition, but alſo doe it by that that is moſt exceeding good, namely, vnder en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuouring to ſerue the law &amp; will of God? So that it can hardly be defined, whether it bee more egregious for the ill it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth, or for the good it peruerteth. Wherein it abuſeth both the good &amp; the ill, with ſuch exquiſite skill, as that it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth notably the duty of both, that is, it doeth grieue, hurt and deſtroy, which is proper vnto euill, and yet winneth it
<pb facs="tcp:173760:37"/>ſelfe neuertheleſſe to be beloued, deſired, and imbraced, which is proper vnto good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Loe, this is a ſtrange kind of ill indeed, that can both grieue a man, and make him loue his griefe; hurt a man, and cauſe him deſire his hurt, and bring him to imbrace all kind of miſery, and euen then to thinke himſelfe in the middeſt of all kind of feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city; to make him blinde in trueth, and yet beleeue that he doth ſee; poore in workes, and yet beleeue that hee is rich; naked of grace, and yet conceiue that he is clothed; wretched in ſtate, and yet bee perſwaded that he is bleſſed: finally, damned, and yet beleeue that he is ſaued.</p>
            <p>Wherein is declared the feareful iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, as our Sauiour witneſſeth, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6. <hi>That he is come vnto iudgement,</hi> that theſe that do ſee the truth, &amp; will not, ſhall be made blind, that they cannot: and thoſe that cannot ſee the truth, and yet would, might bee made able, that they ſhould: For it is a iuſt puniſhment of ſin, that euery one ſhould loſe that gift, that hee would
<pb facs="tcp:173760:38"/>not vſe well when he had it, as <hi>Aug.</hi> ſaith, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de libero arbitrio, Vt cum rectum facere, cum poſsit, non vult, amittat poſſe cum velit.</hi> And euen this iudgement of God is the reaſon, that the recuſant Iuſticiaries of our time, do ſo ſtifly perſiſt in the obſtinacy of their owne wils, as they both refuſe to heare the word preached, leſt it ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them, as alſo all indifferent writers, leſt they ſhould conuince them. What way may a man deuiſe then to perſwade them, ſeeing they will heare no meſſage out of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but euen rake vp their great grand father <hi>Pelagius,</hi> to tell them this tale out of hell? Ye madde men, what? do you meane to make your ſelues mates with Chriſt? to match mans merits, with Gods mercy? to couple humane works, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine grace? &amp; your deſeruing, with Chriſts redeeming? In thus dealing with your ſelues, you doe but damne your ſelues, as ye may behold by me, what deſert is due to you; moſt extreme wrath, for contemning of grace. Ye may not patch an olde gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with new cloth, nor powre new wine
<pb facs="tcp:173760:38"/>into old bottles, but muſt be either al new, or all old; all hote, or all cold; all <hi>Moſes,</hi> or all Chriſt; all works, or all grace: for in the act of ſaluation, there can by no meanes be any botching of new and olde; merits and grace; workes and fayth; heauen and earth; God and man both together. Alas, ſayth <hi>Gregory, Humana iuſticia, diuinae iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciae comparata, iniuſticia eſt: quia vt lucerna in tenebris lucere cernitur, &amp;c.</hi> For euen as a candle in the dark night doth ſhine with brightnes, but in the bright ſunne, is ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed in darknes: ſo humane righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes may ſhine before men, in darknes, but cannot but bee darkened by the ſhining righteouſnes of God.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore take heed, leſt by erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious opinions, we preferre the peruerſnes of our owne wils, before the Law of God, which is the pleaſure of his will, leſt hee make the law (I ſay, his reuealed will) to be a trayne to the frowardnes of our owne will, to bring vs by the conſent of our froward will, vnto deſtruction, according to the iuſt purpoſe of his vvill.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173760:39"/>
            <p> And thus haue ye heard both the foule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the cauſe, and of the crime.</p>
            <p>NOw followeth to bee expreſſed, <hi>The greatneſſe of the payne,</hi> which is no leſſe, then to be <hi>vomited out of the Lords mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereby if this were only meant, that all Neuters, for their hypocriſy and diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, ſhould be caſt out of fauor with the Sonne of God, it were a moſt wofull and importable chaſtiſement, if we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his diuine nature rightly, what the Sonne of God is, that is the ſame God, that is vnto vs the cauſe of all our being, the fountayne of all life, the founder of all ioy, &amp; the mirrour of all goodnes: for he is the Word eternall, that is, God almighty; by whom all things are made, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is life, and of whoſe fulneſſe we receyue what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer good we haue.</p>
            <p>Whereby it muſt of neceſſity follovv, that vvithout the fauour of this vniuerſall cauſe, vvhich is all in all, vvee muſt needs be annihilated to nothing; and being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, yet remayne ſuch a thing notvvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, as is vvithout him; in death, vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:173760:39"/>life; ſubſiſting, without being; deſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, vvithout dying; in life, neuer ioying; in death, euer dying.</p>
            <p>But now, by this <hi>vomiting,</hi> is meant more then a bare eiecting out of fauour: for herein is expreſſed a fearefull and violent caſting out in anger: For in this Simile, the Church is compared to the ſtomacke; the luke-warme Neuter, to the luke-warm water; and their grieuous diſturbance, to noyſome vomitings.</p>
            <p>The Church is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to the ſtomacke, becauſe, as the ſtomacke by altering and concocting the nouriſhment receyued, feedeth &amp; preſerueth the parts of the body: ſo the Church, by concocting &amp; diſgeſting the food of life, doth nouriſh and preſerue the body of Chriſt, euen in ſuch ſort, as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of food in the ſtomack, the liuer draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth bloud; the hart, ſpirit; the brayn, ſence; the ſinewes, ſtrength; the veynes, nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; the body, life: ſo out of the food of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, which is the word of God, that is in the Church, to euery me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of Chriſt, doth the hart draw faith; the wil, obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce;
<pb facs="tcp:173760:40"/>the vnderſtanding, knowledge; the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, comfort; the body, immortality; and the ſoule, all felicity: and that alſo, after ſo rare and ſtupendious an order, that euen as the ſtomake, ſo doeth it quicken, by killing; reuiue, by deſtroying; grow wiſe, by foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhnes; obey, by rebelling againſt its owne fleſh; obtayne life, through death; felicity, through miſery; and eternity out of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.</p>
            <p>The Neuters are compared vnto luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme water, which to a taſting ſtomack, being receiued, is hurtfull; whiles it remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, is grief-ful; &amp; being eiected, is ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: becauſe all Neuters are euen ſuch in the Church of God, not only by hindring the worke of Gods Spirit in the Church, but alſo by the vnquieting and diſturbing of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Their great and grieuous diſturbings are compared to noyſome vomitings; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as that which breedeth vomiting, is caſt out with hatred, for that it is enemy to nature; with violence, becauſe it oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the ſtomacke; with ſhamefulneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:173760:40"/>the defilings thereof are laid open to the eye; and finally, ſo eiected, as neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne to be receyued. So all incorrigible Neuters, ſhall by the LORD himſelfe be throwne out of the Church, as filthy vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitings out of the ſtomacke, &amp; that, with hatred, becauſe they are enemies vnto Chriſt; and with violence, becauſe they hurt and oppreſſe the Church; and vvith ſhame, becauſe their hypocriſy ſhalbe made knowne; &amp; finally, caſt out of the Church, neuer againe to be receyued; becauſe that while they were in the Church, they could neuer bee amended: where the hatred of eiection doeth ſhew the deteſtation of the crime; the violence, the mightineſſe of the payne; the ſhame, the horror of confuſion; and the neuer receyuing, the eternity of deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Then, if it be ſuch a wofull thing, as it hath bene declared, for Neuters to be caſt out of fauour with the Sonne of God, what is it (I pray you) thus to endure the fierceneſſe of his anger? If it be ſo miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, to be depriued of the comfort of his
<pb facs="tcp:173760:41"/>goodneſſe, how importable, to beare the heauy wrath of his greatnes? who is to the wicked, in terrour, the God of venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; in nature, conſuming fire; in wrath, burning ielouſie; his face, lightning; his voyce, thunder; his diſpleaſure, death; his breath, a riuer of brimſtone; his lippes, a floud of indignation; his tongue, a deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring flame; as the Lord doeth witneſſe of himſelfe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 32. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 30. where the mighty terrour of Gods eternall Maieſty is deſcribed, to make it knowne, that as the peruerſnes of ſinners is incorrigible, ſo his wrath towards them is implacable; and as Neuters faults are intolerable, ſo their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments are vnmeaſureable, that ſo there may be a proportion of iuſtice betweene their crime, and his doome; that euen as in this world they would neuer want ſin, ſo in the world to come, they ſhould neuer want payne.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to conclude, ſeeing that the wrath of God, is in this fearefull maner reueyled from heauen, againſt all vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and vnrighteouſnes of men, how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb facs="tcp:173760:41"/>are we here to conſider of our ſelues, how neere this reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſion may touch vs.</p>
            <p>All men, by the cenſure of Chriſt, are either hote in Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or of neceſſity cold, or elſe only luke-warm; &amp; ſo, either Saints in piety, miſcreants in iniquity, or Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for hypocriſy. What may herein iuſtly be deemed of vs? are we Saints? (I would to God we all were, as no doubt, but the Lord hath his.) Let euery man iudge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: if wee be Saints, where is then our workes? if miſcreants, where is then our comfort? if Neuters, where is then our conſcience, when the Sonne of God ſhall come in flaming fire, rendring recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto them that doe not know God, and which obey not the Goſpell of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt? Are wee baptized with the ſpirit and with fire? are we feruent in ſpirit? lucent in life? ardent in zeale? ſhining in works? burning in loue? or in the middeſt of light, remayning in darknes? in the time of truth, abiding in errour? in theſe dayes of grace, liue ſtill in ſinne? nay, are we not cold rather, which euery where preferre
<pb facs="tcp:173760:42"/>pleaſure before piety, that we will take no payne, no, not to purchaſe ioy? which eſteeme of gayne ſo much aboue godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that we wil take no loſſe, no, not to win heauen, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all affections grow ſo cold, in reſpect of Lady Money, that for her loue, men are brought euen vniuerſally to be vniuſt to their owne neighbours; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull to their owne friends; vnkinde to their owne kinne; vnnaturall to their owne parents; vntruſty to their owne Country; vntrue to their owne Prince; impious to their owne God; mercileſſe to all others; &amp; moſt miſerable to their own ſelues. And yet, we are not onely thus too cold; but contrarywiſe, as much too hote: too cold, becauſe wee want zeale; too hote, becauſe wee want patience; too colde, becauſe wee want charity; too hote, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee want modeſty; too cold, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee want fidelity; too hote, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee want our willes.</p>
            <p>If this bee true (beloued) whereof ſhould I firſt complayne? Of our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefulneſſe? or our vngodlineſſe? Our
<pb facs="tcp:173760:42"/>vngratefulneſſe, that whereas God hath made our Countrey, eſpecially this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, a City of viſions, a Sanctuary of Nations, a Crowne and Ioy of all Lands, that after ſo many graces and kindneſſes towards vs, wee ſhould bee towards him, neither new nor old in profeſſion, hote nor cold in affection, fiſh nor fleſh in Religion, light nor darknes in conuerſation: Our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe, to make the Church of God, and houſe of Saints, by our defilings, an habitation for Dragons, <hi>Reu.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>If this be not true, then what argue theſe daily contentions amongſt vs; this mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold cunning and couzenage in all ſorts; this generall deceyt in all trades; this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon lying in all contracts; this priuy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuing of all hands; this ſhouldering and countenancing againſt all right; this extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; oppreſſing on all parts; this immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate licenciouſnes to all luſt; &amp; this defiling of our ſelues with all vice? Hath the Lord therefore giuen vs the diuineneſſe of his truth, goodnes of peace, greatnes of plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſweetnes of health, brightnes of honor,
<pb facs="tcp:173760:43"/>that we liuing in tranquility, in ſafety, in ſecurity, ſhould misſpend our liues in all licenciouſnes and voluptuouſnes of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; after ſo long preaching of the Goſpel, to be a great part counterfets of holineſse, ſerpents of wilineſſe, Satans of wickednes, monſters of vglineſse, &amp; dung-hils of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe?</p>
            <p>Oh, how often hath the Lord admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed vs of theſe monſtrous and prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous behauiours, by monſters and prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies of the land? How often hath hee threatned by Commets &amp; ſignes from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen? And yet we ſtill remayne more dead &amp; ſenceleſſe then the earth: nay the dead and ſenceleſse earth hath generally qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, yet we haue neuer bene abaſhed; the great &amp; mighty waters haue ſtarted backe, and changed the courſe of the ſtreames, yet haue not wee changed the courſe of our liues. The enemies ſword hath beene ready to cut our throats, yet are not wee ready to cut off our ſinnes. The meat hath bin plucked, for our vnworthineſſe, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of our iawes, yet haue not wee repented
<pb facs="tcp:173760:43"/>our diſobedience. The Plague of Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence hath gone ouer our land; and now the poyſon rageth in this the head City of the ſame; yet are not we cured of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, wounds and ſores of our impoyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned corruptions.</p>
            <p>How hath the Land beene ſhaken by deepe and ſecret Treaſons, whileſt wee haue remayned leſſe moueable then the rockes!</p>
            <p>Why? if the Lord can neyther winne vs by his bounty, nor allure vs by his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, nor perſwade vs by his trueth, nor make vs heedfull by his warning, nor feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full by threatning, what ſhall become of vs? Are wee better then the Laodiceans? or will God ſpare vs, that hath ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly puniſhed them? Nay rather, as God hath for their Neutrality caſt out them, ſo will hee likewiſe, for our hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy, vomit out vs.</p>
            <p>All theſe Churches of Aſia there men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, the many and mighty kingdomes of Greece, with the late noble Realmes of Hungary and Liuonia, may at this day
<pb facs="tcp:173760:44"/>be ſpectacles of calamity, to forewarne vs, if wee bee wiſe; who, becauſe they trode vnder foot the eternall verity of the Saints of God, by their filthy life, are now trodden themſelues vnder foot, by the filthy Turke, &amp; euery man of them by ſo much the more abuſed, as he is the more enriched with the ornaments of grace.</p>
            <p>In like maner aſſure your ſelues, if we liue profanely vnder the protection of Gods holy Name, he will take away the Goſpell of the Kingdome from vs, and giue it to a Nation, that ſhall bring forth the fruites of it. And the more that his loue hath beene towards vs, the more will his wrath bee, to recompence the greatneſſe of benefits, with the greatnes of puniſhments, if by our coldnes we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke him thereunto.</p>
            <p>Which plagues, that GOD may turne away from vs, let vs humbly pray him, to turne our hearts towards him, that we may withall our hearts ſerue him, and hee with all his goodneſſe bleſſe vs; that wee paſſing the tyme of this our
<pb facs="tcp:173760:44"/>pilgrimage in his feare, may paſſe the reſt of the time in his ioy, to the prayſe of the glory and rich grace, which hee hath towards vs in IESVS CHRIST. To whome, with the Father, and the holy Spirit, three Perſons and one God, bee aſcribed all honour and glory, prayſe and thanksgiuing, for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
